beautiful. CHAPTER 12 It was on the 9th of November, the eve
of his own 38th birthday, as he often remembered afterwards. He was walking
home about 11:00 from Lord Henry’s, where he had been dining, and was wrapped in
heavy furs, as the night was cold and foggy. At the corner of grova Square and
South odley Street, a man passed him in the mist, walking very fast and with the
collar of his gray ster turned up. He had a bag in his hand. Dorian recognized him.
It was Basil Hallward. A strange sense of fear, for which he could not account, came over him.
He made no sign of recognition and went on quickly in the direction of his own
house. But hallwood had seen him. Dorian heard him first stopping on the pavement
and then hurrying after him. In a few moments, his hand was on his
arm. “Dorian! What an extraordinary piece of luck I've been waiting for you in
your library ever since 9:00 Finally I took pity on your tired
servant and told him to go to bed, as he
let me out I'm off to Paris by the midnight train, and I particularly wanted
to see you before I left. I thought it was you, or rather your fur coat, as you
passed me. But I wasn’t quite sure. Didn’t you recognize me?” “In this fog, my dear
Basil? Why, I can’t even recognize grov no Square. I believe my house is somewhere
about here, but I don’t feel at all certain about it I'm sorry you are going
away, as I've not seen you for ages. But I suppose you will be back soon?” “No I'm
going to be out of England for 6 months.
I intend to take a studio in Paris and shut myself up till I have finished a
great picture I have in my head. However, it wasn’t about myself I wanted to
talk. Here we are at your door. Let me come in for a moment. I have something to
say to you.” “I shall be charmed. But won’t you miss your train?”
said Dorian Gray languidly as he passed up the steps and opened the door with his latch key
The lamp light struggled out through the fog, and hallwood looked at his
watch. “I have heaps of time,” he answered.
“The train doesn’t go till 12:15 and it's
only just 11: In fact, I was on my way to
the club to look for you, when I met you.
You see, I Shan have any delay about luggage, as I have sent on my heavy
things. All I have with me is in this bag,
and I can easily get to Victoria in 20 minutes
looked at him and smiled. “What a way for a fashionable painter to travel! A
gladston bag and an ulster! Come in, or the fog will get into the house. And mind
you don’t talk about anything serious.
Nothing is serious nowadays. At least nothing should be hallwood shook his head, as he entered,
and followed Dorian into the library. There was a bright wood fire
blazing in the large open hearth. The lamps were lit, and an open Dutch silver
Spirit case stood, with some siphons of soda water and large cut glass tumblers,
on a little marer table. “You see your servant made me quite
at home, Dorian. He gave me everything I wanted, including your best gold tipped
cigarettes. He is a most hospitable creature. I like him much better than the
Frenchman you used to have. What has become of the Frenchman, by the
by Dorian shrugged his shoulders. “I believe he married Lady Radley’s maid,
and has established her in Paris as an English dress maker anglomania is very
fashionable over there now, I hear seems silly of the French, doesn’t it? But— —do
you know?— ?—he was not at all a bad servant. I never liked him, but I had
nothing to complain about. One often imagines things that are quite
absurd. He was really very devoted to me and seemed quite sorry when he went
away. Have another Brandy and soda Or would you like Hawk and seltzer I always
take Haw and seltzer myself. There is sure to be some in the next
room.” “Thanks, I won’t have anything more,” said the painter, taking his cap and coat
off and throwing them on the bag that he had placed in the
corner. “And now, my dear fellow, I want to speak to you seriously. Don’t frown like
that. You make it so much more difficult for me.” “What is it all about?” cried Dorian in
his petulent way, flinging himself down on the sofa. “I hope it is not about myself I'm
tired of myself tonight I should like to be somebody else.” “It is about yourself,”
answered hallwood in his grave deep voice, “and I must say it to you. I shall
only keep you half an hour.” Dorian sighed and lit a cigarette. “Half an hour!” he
murmured. “It is not much to ask of you, Dorian, and it is entirely for your own
sake that I'm speaking. I think it right that you should know that the most dreadful
things are being said against you in life London.” “I don’t wish to know
anything about them. I love scandals about other people, but scandals about
myself don’t interest me. They have not got the charm of novelty.” “They must interest you,
Dorian. Every gentleman is interested in his good name. You don’t want people to
talk of you as something vile and degraded. Of course, you have your
position, and your wealth, and all that kind of thing. But position and wealth are not
everything. Mind you, I don’t believe these rumors at all. At least, I can’t
believe them when I see you. Sin is a thing that writes itself across a man’s
face. It cannot be concealed. People talk sometimes of secret vices. There are no
such things. If a wretched man has a vice, it shows itself in the lines of his
mouth, the droop of his eyelids, the molding of his hands even. Somebody— —I
won’t mention his name, but you know him— —came to me last year to have his port
done I'd never seen him before, and had never heard anything about him at the
time, though I have heard a good deal since. He offered an extravagant price. I
refused him. There was something in the shape of his fingers that I
hated. I know now that I was quite right in what I fancied about him. His life is
dreadful. But you, Dorian, with your pure, bright, innocent face, and your marvelous
untroubled youth— —I can’t believe anything against you. And yet I see you
very seldom, and you never come down to the studio now, and when I'm away from
you, and I hear all these hideous things that people are whispering about you, I
don’t know what to say. Why is it, Dorian,
that a man like the Duke of bar leaves
the room of a club when you enter it? Why is it that so many gentlemen in London
will neither go to your house or invite you to theirs? You used to be a friend of
Lord stavely I met him at dinner last week. Your name happened to come up in
conversation, in connection with the miniatures you have lent to the exhibition at the
Dudley stavely curled his lip and said that you might have the most artistic
tastes, but that you were a man whom no pure-minded girl should be allowed to
know, and whom no chased woman should sit in the same room with. I reminded him
that I was a friend of yours, and asked
him what he meant. He told me. He told me right out before everybody. It was horrible!
Why is your friendship so fatal to young men? There was that wretched boy in the
Guards who committed suicide. You were his great friend. There
was Sir Henry Ashton, who had to leave England with a tarnished name. You and he were
inseparable. What about Adrien Singleton and his dreadful end? What about Lord
Kent’s only son and his career? I met his father yesterday in St.
James’s Street. He seemed broken with shame and sorrow. What about the young
Duke of Perth? What sort of life has he got now? What gentleman would associate with
him?” “Stop, Basil. You are talking about things of which you know nothing,” said
Dorian Gray, biting his lip, and with a note of infinite contempt in his voice.
“You ask me why baric leaves a room when I enter it. It is because I know
everything about his life, not because he knows anything about mine. With such
blood as has in his veins, how could his record be clean? You asked me about Henry
Ashton and young Perth. Did I teach the one his vices, and the other his
debauchery? If Kent’s silly son takes his wife from the streets, what is that to me?
If Adrien Singleton writes his friend’s name across a bill, am I his keeper? I
know how people chatter in England. The middle classes he their moral prejudices
over their gross dinner tables and whisper about what they call the profaci
of their betters in order to try and pretend that they are in smart society
and on intimate terms with the people they slander. In this country, it is enough for
a man to have distinction and brains for every common tongue to wag against him.
And what sort of lives do these people, who pose as being moral, lead themselves?
My dear fellow, you forget that we are in the native land of the
hypocrite.” “Dorian,” cried hallwood that is not the question. England is bad enough I
know, and English society is all wrong.
That is the reason why I want you to be
fine. You have not been fine. One has a
right to judge of a man by the effect he has over his friends. Yours seem to lose
all sense of honor of goodness, of purity.
You have filled them with a madness for pleasure. They have gone down into the
depths. You led them there. Yes: you led them there,
and yet you can smile, as you are smiling now. And there is worse
behind. I know you and Harry are inseparable. Surely for that reason, if
for none other, you should not have made his sister’s name a
byword Take care, Basil. You go too far.” “I must speak, and you must listen. You shall
listen. When you met Lady gwendaline not a breath of scandal had had ever touched
her. Is there a single decent woman in London now who would drive with her in the
park? Why, even her children are not allowed to live with her. Then there are
other stories— —stories that you have been seen creeping at dawn out of dreadful
houses and slinking in disguise into the foulest dens in London. Are they true? Can they be
true? When I first heard them, I laughed. I hear them now, and they make me
shudder. What about your country house and the life that is led there? Dorian,
you don’t know what is said about
you. I won’t tell you that I don’t want
to preach to you. I remember Harry saying once that every man who turned himself
into an amateur curate for the moment always began by saying that, and then
proceeded to break his word. I do want to
preach to you. I want you to lead such a life as will make the world respect
you. I want you to have a clean name and
a fair record. I want you to get rid of the dreadful people you associate with.
Don’t shrug your shoulders like that.
Don’t be so indifferent. You have a wonderful influence. Let it be for good, not for
evil. They say that you corrupt everyone with whom you become intimate, and that
it is quite sufficient for you to enter a house for shame of some kind to follow
after. I don’t know whether it is so or
not. How should I know? But it is said of you I'm told things that it seems
impossible possible to doubt. Lord glester was one of my greatest friends
at Oxford. He showed me a letter that his wife had written to him when she was
dying alone in her villa at Menon Your name was implicated in the
most terrible confession I ever read. I told him that it was absurd— —that I knew
you thoroughly, and that you were incapable of anything of the kind. Know
you? I wonder do I know you? Before I could answer that, I should have to see your
soul.” “To see my soul!” muttered Dorian Gray, starting up from the sofa and turning
almost white from fear. “Yes,” answered hallwood gravely, and
with deep toned sorrow in his voice, “to see your
soul. But only God can do that.” A bitter laugh of mockery broke from the lips of
the younger man. “You shall see it yourself tonight he cried, seizing a lamp
from the table. “Come: it is your own handy work Why shouldn’t you look at it? You
can tell the world all about it afterwards, if you choose. Nobody would
believe you. If they did believe you, they would like me all the better for it. I
know the age better than you do, though you will prate about it so
tediously. Come, I tell you. You have chattered enough about corruption. Now
you shall look on it face to face.” There was the madness of pride in every word he
uttered. He stamped his foot upon the ground in his boyish insolent manner. He
felt a terrible joy at the thought that someone else was to share his secret, and
that the man who had painted the portrait that was the origin of all his
shame was to be burdened for the rest of his life with the hideous memory of what
he had done. “Yes,” he continued, coming closer to him and looking steadfastly into his
stern eyes, “I shall show you my soul. You shall see the thing that you fancy only
God can see hallwood started back. “This is blasphemy,
Dorian!” he cried. “You must not say things like that. They are horrible, and they
don’t mean anything.” “You think so?” He laughed again. “I know so. As for what I
said to you tonight I said it for your good. You know I have been always a
stanch friend to you.” “Don’t touch me.
Finish what you have to say.” A twisted flash of pain shot across
the painter’s face. He paused for a moment, and a wild feeling of pity came
over him. After all, what right had he to pry into the life of Dorian Gray? If he
had done a tithe of what was rumored about him, how much he must have suffered!
Then he straightened himself up, and walked over to the fireplace and stood
there, looking at the burning logs with their frost-like ashes and their throbbing cores of
flame I'm waiting, Basil,” said the young man in a hard clear voice. He turned
round. “What I have to say is this,” he cried. “You must give me some answer to
these horrible charges that are made against you. If you tell me that they are
absolutely untrue from beginning to end, I shall believe you. Deny them, Dorian,
deny them! Can’t you see what I'm going through? My God! don’t tell me that you
are bad, and corrupt, and shameful.” Dorian Gray smiled. There was a curl of cont tempt in his
lips. “Come upstairs, Basil,” he said quietly.
“I keep a diary of my life from day to day, and it never leaves the room in
which it is written. I shall show it to you if you come with
me.” “I shall come with you, Dorian, if you wish it. I see I've missed my train. That
makes no matter. I can go tomorrow But don’t ask me to read anything tonight
All I want is a plain answer to my question.” “That shall be given to you upstairs. I
could not give it here. You will not have to read long.” CHAPTER